We need to stop thinking on LLMs as the
only solution. Apple released an open
source model to do some image detection.
It's a model of 200 megabytes and works
client side. So, now you can have an OCR
system that can detect objects
completely local. It opens a lot
opportunities for a lot of apps and web
apps that can run even without internet,
just offline, and you don't need LLMs.
>> Tell us a little bit about your recent
work and focus on Web MCP, like what it
is and what problem it's trying to
solve.
>> Right now, ChatGPT agent mode or Claude
agent mode, okay, they're browsing the
website typically in just taking a
screenshots and then saying, "Oh, I'm
analyzing with an image model." But then
they trigger the click on that portion
of the screen. But what happens if in
those 5 to 10 seconds the JavaScript
moved that button? That is inefficient
both in time and in cost. And that's
where Web MCP appears as a solution. Web
MCP is kind of an API. It's just
JavaScript functions that you expose to
the agent. Instead of browsing the
website as a human, it will just execute
those functions.
>> [music]
>> Back in November, we hosted the first
ever in-person AI Native Dev Con in New
York. This June 1st and 2nd, [music]
we're bringing it to London. It's 2 days
built for AI Native developers and
engineering [music] teams. One day full
of hands-on workshops and one day full
of practical talks on agent skills,
context engineering, agent orchestration
and enablement platforms, [music]
and how teams are actually shipping AI
in production.
Join us at The Brewery in London near
the Barbican for all of that plus
>> [music]
>> networking, parties, giveaways, and a
room full of people building the future
[music] of AI Native development. You
can also join us from anywhere in the
world via the live stream.
As you're listening to this podcast, you
get 30% off your ticket with code pod30.
Just head to ainativedevcon.io
and we'll see you in London.
Hello, everyone. Welcome back to the AI
Native Dev. Uh today we will be jumping
into the world of the web, which uh is
is actually a fun space because my
background in sort of the
entrepreneurial world has been in um
making websites faster, especially with
the rise of the mobile web. And that's
where I got to meet Max, who is kind of
been building up uh you know, a ton in
the web at the time, was optimizing for
mobile performance, for responsive
websites, you know, for many aspects of
the the rise of the mobile web, and
today is in AI world. So, Max, thanks
for coming on to the show here. I'm a
pleasure. Thank you. I can kind of wax
poetic a little bit about your
background. Probably best to for you to
describe the journey, uh but it's so
tell us a little bit of just for people
to have the the mindset of where is your
information coming from, a bit about
your uh your experience. Yeah, sure. So,
I've been a a web developer for 30
years. So, that's a lot. 30 years now.
So, I have started doing websites in
1995, actually.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, I was actually So, my first
website was created in the edit
of DOS.
So, we are talking in text mode. And
then I was getting into Windows 3.1,
opening Netscape, and opening manually
the HTML files to see how it looks like.
So, that was
the the idea at the time. And yeah, in
my journey I I So, I've seen everything.
So, from all the different design
patterns, all the different languages,
like ASP, PHP, then then the the move to
the front, the the web 2.0
stuff, HTML5.
And on on mobiles, I'm also a mobile
developer, so native native iOS, native
Android. I did Objective-C, Kotlin then
or Java for Android, then Kotlin. Uh and
I I was like the like the the the merge
of the two worlds, the mobile and the
web. So, I I authored a couple of books
on the mobile web, then moving into the
performance side of that. So, I I
authored a couple of books on on the
mobile web as well.
So, I have books on JavaScript. So, I
actually I'm I'm authoring right now,
even right now in the AI era,
uh like an old-fashioned book. So, then
that's going to be my 15th book. And
which are you using AI in uh in the
writing of this book?
Actually, no. And that's part of the
part of the deal. So, I'm writing a book
on vanilla web. So, how to to write
websites without the libraries that
actually is useful on the AI world
because it's better for context and and
things like that. So, it's better for
agentic AI tools to code some web apps
without a lot of dependencies. So,
that's kind of my journey. And of
course, as every developer, because I'm
a developer, I'm in AI era right now.
So, there is no other way, no other
option. So, that's why I've started
doing even some courses on on working
with ChatGPT 3 years ago. So, as soon as
the API was released from Open AI, I
started doing articles and content and
courses on how to integrate your
websites, your apps with
uh Open AI APIs, how to do prompt
engineering for for your apps, things
like that. And as soon as um also
ChatGPT, because I'm telling I'm saying
ChatGPT because it was the first one.
When they created the first browsing
plugin,
I started doing a research on how uh is
that working. So, how is ChatGPT
rendering your website? How it how does
work? So, if you want to optimize your
content for that, how to do that? So, I
started writing some articles on that.
And technology is evolving every day,
actually.
You We know that. So, there is a fever
right now on that. So, I'm trying to
keep updated on every every new
technology, design pattern, tool uh that
will help developers to to merge into
this AI world. Yeah. No, amazing. And I
yeah, it is, you know, fever is a good
is a good word for it. There's
definitely, you know, some intensity
around the pace of change of it that is
exhilarating and daunting at the
uh at the same time. So, um what
triggered this conversation is your
recent work and focus on Web MCP.
Uh and I found that super interesting as
I as I think about your the problem at a
high level resonated with me that uh it
felt like agents keep needing to reverse
engineer uh uh a web page and they
arrive there and they, you know, they
try to kind of find the signals on it.
They're doing it impressively well,
uh but it still feels somewhat
inefficient. So, it really kind of
caught my attention when I when I saw
the the title and I think you had some a
big tweet that got some uh some big
uh big reach around it. So, maybe let's
start the conversation by just digging
into Web MCP. Tell us a little bit about
first of all, like what it is and what
problem it's trying to solve. Okay,
yeah, sure. So, Web MCP is first is an
experimental API that is still not
stable.
It's uh it was presented by the Chrome
team. So, it's right now working in
Google Chrome under a flag.
And the idea is to offer AI agents
another way to use the web app services.
Because right now, when when I'm when
we're talking about AI agents, we are
talking about
ChatGPT agent mode or uh
Claude agent mode, okay, or Gemini. But
also we are talking about Open Claw that
is maybe browsing the website and also
agentic browsers.
So, that's ChatGPT Atlas,
uh Perplexity browser, even now Google
Chrome or Microsoft Edge. They have an
AI mode or an agent mode that they can
browse the website for you.
But right now, they're browsing the
website typically in two ways. The most
common way is just taking a screenshots
and then saying, "Oh, I'm analyzing with
an image model, analyzing the image, and
saying, 'Oh, I need to click here in
those coordinates.'" And then that takes
time, couple of seconds.
But then they trigger the click on that
portion of the screen.
But what happens if in those 5 to 10
seconds the JavaScript moved that
button? Okay? So, it doesn't work. So,
then another screenshot is taken and
then the agent says, "Oh, maybe the
website was scrolled or the content
changed or whatever." So, that is
inefficient both in time and in cost
because that's in in tokens, okay? We
need to pay for that. How uh like why
are they doing images versus
understanding the web page itself? Well,
the other the other way to do that,
that's the most common way. The other
way is to kind of analyzing the DOM.
Okay? Um the thing is that the DOM, you
know, we we've been
mostly after
the React world,
the when when you look at the DOM that
we are shipping to the user, it's not
semantic.
So, it's just a a list of 100 divs. Divs
is just a generic tag that you have on a
website that has no semantics. So,
actually understanding
what's there with just the DOM might not
be useful on every on every website.
Right. So, on for example, on mobile
apps, on native mobile apps, for
example, if you want an agent to use an
iOS application in your iPhone,
so, you can also do screenshots,
but also they have some kind of an
accessibility tree that is actually
really useful because it's the same tree
that accessibility tools such as a
screen readers are using to
understanding your app. So, I think
that's um
that's that's pretty cool. And on the
web
you can do something like that, but it
seems like uh on some test, the the
results are not really good. So, that's
why most of them are still using the old
way of taking a screenshot. Okay?
So, which
works, but it's com-
completely efficient. And I think that
makes sense, I guess when you when you
describe it like if you try to build an
application today, it's so dynamic, you
know, it is
uh you know, sort of changes all the
time on it, but it's also
really hard to decipher. Like even as an
as an expert developer opening up that
DOM, figuring out what's what without
looking at the visual is actually quite
hard.
>> Well, it's optimized for a human brain
actually, right? So, it's optimized for
for that. So, that's kind that kind of
the agent is still um
it can do that, but on a screenshot. And
that's where WebMCP appears as a
solution. The idea is that WebMCP is
kind of an API.
So, the the web app developer
will expose an API to the agent. Saying,
"Hey agent, if you want to like talk
with to me to my website, here you have
a couple of services that I can
provide."
So, you register a list of services or
tools that you make available to the
agent.
And it's just JavaScript functions that
you expose to the agent. So, then the
agent when when the agent is browsing a
WebMCP capable website it will check all
the services available and it will try
to see if one of those services is uh
suitable
for the goal that it has. And instead of
browsing the website as a human with the
eye and the hand touching on the screen,
it will just execute those functions. In
this context, the the service provider
of these functions is the web page. It's
not necessarily the thing behind the
screen. So, services can be anything
that can that local execution can
satisfy. You know, things like click a
button, give me some piece of content on
the page. Like what are examples of
services that that you see people
starting to build? The service executes
on the client, so in in JavaScript, so
on the web page. But that service can
also use normal web APIs to connect to
the cloud, to connect to a hardware
using Bluetooth or whatever. So,
actually, the simplest example is an
airline website. So, you get into an
airline website and you are searching
for flights. So, you need you need to go
to the one text field that says uh your
origin, then your destination, then you
need to open the calendar or type the
date. And you know that every airline is
different, so the calendar is different.
So, the agent has to understand how the
calendar works.
Well, in instead of that you offer
just a tool, a function that is search
flights. You uh specify the schema of
the input data. So, you're going to
specify to the agent, "Hey, I need
origin, destination, and two dates."
And and if it's one way or round trip
whatever you want to define there, and a
function. And and you actually pass a
JavaScript function to the WebMCP API
and say, "When the agent wants to
execute this, this is the function." On
that function, you can do local stuff
or you can go to your own server, your
own back end, or whatever you are used
to do on on the website. Actually, you
can share the functions with your uh
standard UI.
There is a flag that you can check if if
currently an agent executing this or a
user executing this in case you want to
do things differently, but you can you
can um take advantage of your current
architecture
and just call that. And you will return
asynchronously. So, that's why the agent
will wait for you. And in in that wait,
you can go to the cloud, you can go to a
hardware, a sensor, or or even you can
ask the user.
So, there are some some for example, if
you are
uh ordering or you are confirming
something that will have a cost you as a
web app developer, you can say, "Hey
agent, you know what? I would need to
ask the user." So, the API includes a
way for you to interrupt the agent and
call the user. Yeah, you don't you you
you tell the agent that it should ask
the user or do you literally uh No, you
you you ask the browser. You ask the
browser and the browser will say,
"Agent, you know what? You will wait
because I will ask the user." So, in
that it can be a like um a dialogue on
the screen asking the user, "Hey, do you
confirm to actually buy this this
flight?" And if the user say yes, then
you go back to the agent and and confirm
the operation.
>> And this is relevant I guess when the
user is actually actively behind the
browser. So, like these agentic browsers
for instance, it would work for for
them. But if I asked ChatGPT or Claude
some question and it went on and it
uh the stuff, then the browser is not
interacting with me as a as a user,
right? Yeah, I guess that the standard
will
still need to figure that out how So,
how that's going to work with uh It is
important WebMCP as it is right now,
remember experimental feature, works
only on visible browsers. Okay? So, it's
not working on headless browsers.
Got it. Okay, so that's an important
distinction for now. It's not the intent
of the protocol, it's just the original
kind of the initial implementation of
it. Focus on that.
>> And so, how So, if it's the server-side
actions, um
how is this different than having an
API? Like why wouldn't I just have a you
know, an open API spec, you know, that I
make available and properly link from my
side and have the agent just
programmatically interact with my
system? Yeah, well, that's actually a
very good reason. A very good question
because even the same question happens
on the MCP world without the web. So,
MCP is another protocol that we use to
connect AI tools with servers.
>> True. And right now, even Open Claw or
other agents among
uh Claw Co-work for example,
they're I mean, you can connect MCP
tools, but they can just go and execute
uh CLI tools in in the in the terminal.
So, they don't need MCP. So, something
like that happens here on the web. So,
um if you have a RESTful API for example
or another kind of API or an MCP API
or a CLI, then you don't need to use
your website. Yeah, that's and that's um
that's a fair question. I think it has
to do with
with the kind of project that you have
for example. Some tools need
authentication.
Uh they have that they have a lot of uh
maybe local database that you have on
the on the client. So, that tool works
actually better in the browser's context
and from for security from security
purposes. So, you don't want to open the
API to the to the outside.
So, it's kind of a different way
to do that.
But it's important to understand that
WebMCP is not working automatically for
your website. So, you need to actually
go to your JavaScript code and implement
the API. So, it's not going to be
applied automatically. Yeah, and and and
I think that sense it is the same as
building an API. But I I get that.
There's increasingly functionality.
That's why I perceived it initially as
uh something in which the service
provider is the page. The API call, the
WebMCP call, the recipient of it is a
JavaScript function, right? That is um
there's code on the on the page and then
it can do whatever wonders. So, at the
very least when you have rich
functionality on the page, and as you
pointed out, you don't want the agents
to
just kind of do the heavy lifting of
uncovering it within the system, but you
want to give them an agent-friendly
programmatic interface to it to your
client side. So, at the very least for
that, this is this is novel. I guess you
could have
you could have hoped the agent
understands this with some sort of LLM
sticks to whatever it is, but this is a
standardized way to uh to do that. Um
and then there's some overlap between
for server-side activities, there's some
overlap between that and
uh and an open API. Yeah, there is.
Definitely. The but for example, one one
quick example of why WebMCP might be
better than than server-side only.
Uh Apple Pay or Android Pay.
So, if you want to finish the the
payment process and you want to use
Apple Pay
it has to do on the client. So, that
works on the client only. So, you're not
sending the credit card details over
over over the
like a RESTful API.
So, um that's one example on on why you
want to take advantage of the
client-side architecture and you want
the agent to somehow get into that
architecture.
But that's that's one example. So,
that's why typically you will see
shopping carts as examples of how to
where to implement WebMCP.
So, uh the shopping cart lives in the
client, not in the server.
So, then you
uh you can just work with that client
side and and you make an order and that
that making an order is actually the one
that is going to the server anyway. So,
the question of why is the agent not
going directly to the server and making
the order is actually a fair question.
And I think right now it has to do with
more uh
following the standard UX flow.
And instead of just designing a web app
that is 100% optimized for for an agent.
Maybe in the future we will be creating
this system for agents only.
So, then it would be a completely
different architecture.
I think so so very interesting. And you
were saying that in the initial
iteration of it, it is focused on on
visible browsers.
And you're right that that introduces
also that sort of user interaction. So,
some of it is client side, some of it is
user interaction,
and then you know, some of it might be
convenience or sort of you know, like a
preference that you want to prefer. You
You want to provide this via Web MCP
versus Open API.
I
I'm curious about the path or the jump
from there to headless browser. I mean,
per your starting point
description,
you know, like headless browsers also do
this, you know, as unpleasantry of sort
of like trying to grab an image and
reverse engineer
in a variety of ways a webpage. And so,
they probably benefit from even access
to content and things like that on it.
What what is your expectation in terms
of the primary use cases for a headless
browser?
You know, I guess
I don't I don't know what what's your
guess on when does that happen?
Most of these agents are using
Playwright or Puppeteer. So, these tools
that were originally
created for automation. So, browser
automation. So, actually they are
creating a headless browser executing
your your web up there. So, ChatGPT
initially was just
using a tool that was converting the
HTML into markdown. So, it wasn't even
executing JavaScript. So, the initial
ChatGPT plugin was really simple.
And to be honest, if you're browsing if
you're asking ChatGPT or Claude or
Gemini
to to read a website and and summarize
this website and you give the URL, on
most situations, they're still doing
that. They're just downloading a
markdown version
of your HTML. So, if you're if your
website is is 100% client-side
rendering,
it's not going to work. So, it will say
I can't read this website, right? But if
you're using an agent, that's like a
next step, the agent is typically
assuming the user's role. And in that
case, it's using some tools like right
now Playwright, Puppeteer are the most
common one
to try to act as a user. So, in terms of
expectation, I think that we need
I'm not sure if the Google Chrome team
will
think too much about that. So, they are
targeting how to increase the Chrome
agent mode. So, they are working on that
API. So, we need more companies, maybe
OpenAI, maybe now OpenAI that is uh
is the sponsor of Open Claude.
We need them on board of the W3C to
discuss
the API on for those agents. I'm not
seeing them doing that right now. They
were not part of the web community, so
probably something new for them. But
Anthropic that created the MCP protocol
may be also interested in getting into
Web MCP.
I'm not seeing that yet that's happening
yet. Yeah, quite yet, but
I guess that will happen at some point
so in the next few weeks or month month
and that will trigger some updates in
this API. I think that makes sense and I
think Anthropic is actually an
interesting example because they are
actually not that strong around the
image
analysis as compared to some of their
competitors.
So, it's actually kind of interesting
for them to maybe bias in favor of do it
do it correctly. I guess as you So, you
mentioned MCP as well.
I guess what what what's the trigger
behind the Web MCP name? What is similar
and what is different between that and
the the non-Web MCP?
Well, I think that
what is similar is a concept.
If you look at the technical details,
it's it's going to be two different
protocols. So, yeah, MCP works
with with JSON in and out.
It's kind of So, the not Web MCP.
The standard MCP for AI agents, yeah.
They work over different They are
different versions and different
protocols that they work originally.
They were working on HTTP, but using a
using a technique that was really old
that they brought about technique in an
ancient book
30 years ago.
And now they were using that technique
because they were not supporting
sockets, web sockets. So, it was kind of
a long polling technique over HTTP.
But and also they have a socket version
for like a binary socket for local
server and clients. So, when you have a
local thing, you can just
talk with sockets, but
it's a completely different idea. And
you expose but the similar concept is
that you expose your services
to an LLM. And by the way, exposing the
services is just typing a name of the
service and then a description in
English.
And the LLM will understand that
description.
And and the schema that you want. And
that's a formal schema. So, I really
need four arguments. The first one is an
integer, the second is a string, blah
blah blah. Well, the same idea is here,
but
you cannot you cannot just export your
MCP into Web MCP. You need to write it
from a scratch because it's a it's a
completely different architecture. This
is JavaScript. Web MCP is JavaScript
based. It's actually pretty simple from
a coding point of view. You just say
navigator.modelcontext.registertool
and you pass three arguments. The name,
the description in English, like a long
description, and a JavaScript function.
And and that's all.
Yeah. So,
the tool that the agent will actually
query on all those tools. It will read
descriptions and will say, "Oh, I need
to change a flight reservation." Okay,
it will look into all your services to
see if any description matches that
behavior, that tool.
And it will say, "Oh, this one." And it
will execute
that function passing the arguments that
you requested as the input schema.
Yeah. That's roughly how that works. And
your your API will return some data. It
can be a boolean, it can be an integer,
it can be a message, an object. And that
object goes in JSON back to the agent
that will process that with the LLM.
Yeah. It actually I think simplicity is
It's great to hear that it's simple and
I think it's actually
probably one of the things that helped
MCP also get adoption because it creates
something that is very streamlined and
slightly capitalizes on the fact that
you can communicate all sorts of
complexity and things like that in that
natural language line and rely on the
fact that you have a consumer there. And
the same goes for the response, right?
You can You can reply the whole
complexity of what is it that you are
returning
can be simplified because of that. In
that sense, it is a lower lift than any
even REST APIs which were already in
turn a simplification.
But as compared to that, it is still
simple. So, it just lowers the barrier
and just allows allows more of these
types of interfaces to be created. Yeah,
sure. Also, there is even a simpler
version because you can also use the
character version and in that case it's
just HTML. So, you don't even need to
write JavaScript. If you have forms in
your HTML, you add some attributes in
the form and you're specifying to the
agent, "Hey, if you want to
trigger this action, this is the form
and here you have the fields that you
need to fill
for for triggering this action." So, Web
MCP also works in HTML without
JavaScript.
And something interesting is that it's
also adding some ideas that we don't
have right now. For example, as a web
app developer, there is no way to know
if your website is currently being
managed or used by an agent.
So, there is no way. So, if you want to
detect for whatever reason, even for for
analytics, you want to detect that it's
actually an agent using your website,
there is no way to actually do that. So,
on X, Twitter, they they changed
something now to stop agents for
publishing content on on Twitter.
And they say that they are actually
verifying if you're actually if there is
an actual finger touching the screen,
which on the web, I mean, you cannot
actually do that. I mean, you can check
with the touch events if there is a
touch
Yeah, but basically with
any any tool like Puppeteer or
Playwright, you are you can emulate
the touch and the website will never
know it's it's an agent. Well, now with
Web MCP, we have new events
that you can listen in your website over
the window object. This is the
JavaScript technical stuff, but there is
tool activated and tool cancel. That
means that the tool or the agent is it's
it's named tool within the API
is actually controlling the website. So,
then you can change the UI, you can you
can There is also some CSS pseudo
classes that will let you
change the use the the user interface a
little bit when the agent is in charge.
So, then the if the user is actually
seeing the screen, you can
tell the user that the agent is in
charge despite the browser UI that is
also making that that
that notice somehow. Right. Yeah, I
think So, it's interesting to think
about the
drivers for adoption I guess of people
like why would they bother writing this?
And and I think that was one like maybe
I'll go on a tangent a bit and then come
back to that question, which is there is
a broader trend in the world of AI of
unifying things that we used to split
apart. And so, the separation of the API
from your webpage is is something that
in many aspects is good architecture,
right? Like it is the right way to do it
so that the two are not coupled and you
build those. And in in in a sense, here
you're kind of building an API into your
webpage or you're intentionally
violating it, but in in agent land, when
you start creating multiple
uh entities that the agent has to
orchestrate within them, uh it gets
confused. And so, for instance, there's
been a big rise of mono repos, right?
And and pulling everything into the repo
because then, you know, you can just
have the agent load the repo, and it's
all within the reach. And so, it's
interesting to think about like one of
the advantages of a web MCP is that it
puts the API, or it kind of puts the
actions within the web page, and it's a
more contained unit, and therefore
easier for the for the agent to to uh
interact with, right? But coming back a
bit to my uh my uh my question there was
like, what would you say are the are the
top motivations, and I think you've
alluded to a few, for someone to to
embrace this? Like, if I'm Who who would
be the first cohort to come in when this
is no longer experimental, uh which this
is AI land, so maybe that happens faster
than we uh than we think. Um
uh
who would be the the What are the
strongest motivations to to put in the
effort? I think that the strongest
motivation will be uh
will appear on e-commerce websites.
Wherever e-commerce website you have, I
mean, you want to sell products or
services, you actually don't care if
it's a human or an agent. So, you want
the money from the consumer. And so,
that's I mean, that's a motivation to
actually offer as many tools as possible
as fast as possible so they can actually
purchase your products or services
quickly. So, I think that's that's uh
that's the first one. When you look at
other kind of content, I don't know, you
have a blog, you have a newspaper.
Actually, I'm seeing the opposite
sometimes. And so, I'm seeing authors
actually rejecting agents.
So, I don't want the agent to come into
my website. Yeah, more about IP than
content.
>> Yeah, because of IP or because they're
they they user will not get into my
website, they will just get the content,
and I mean, the authority is get gets
out, so there is no credit of that or
not enough credit or whatever. I mean,
you can still apply web MCP there, but I
don't think
it would make a lot of sense.
>> Yeah. So, in a blog or in a newspaper,
but um if you have uh anything that has
to do with uh service support, so if you
have a problem with I don't know, your
your phone bill, uh then your phone
company, your agent, if you're asking
your agent to go and try to solve the
problem, I mean, all that working with
support tickets and all that stuff can
be also another uh pretty useful use
case. E- Either way, it sounds like it
and by definition, you know, by design,
it is oriented at interactive pages. And
so, it will pages that are that are
predominantly content, you know, beyond
their own agenda and sort of like or
dislike of agents, uh it's also probably
a little bit less useful for them. But
if you if you look at if you look at the
API, when when they have when you use
the declarative API, it works on forms.
So, if you have if your website have
forms, then it's it can be a target of
web MCP. If you don't have any form in
your website, it seems like you don't
have a use case. Yeah, there's no no
real need. Uh what about the web
testing? So, we know the the other the
other uh entity that suffers from the
ever-changing visuals of uh of of
websites is the kind of pursuit of
end-to-end testing uh that doesn't
require you to rewrite your tests uh
every uh
every
uh whatever pull request. Um the Is
there a use case for this for like web
MCP to be it it can't do the visual
testing, but to do like a navigation,
you know, to the extent that, you know,
you've blended that it's the same form
that is now marked as tool, right? Or
the same JavaScript function that is
called by the web page and the tool?
Right now, when you're doing end-to-end
testing, uh we're talking about also
tools using uh tools like Playwright and
Puppeteer, and those are the same tools
as the agents are using these days to
browse the website. So, but um I think
that web MCP is more for unit testings
because you're actually testing a
function and see if the function is
working properly. And it looks more than
that like uh the end-to-end
human user testing because that's to do
how how everything looks like. So, I
think that you would still need to do
that um
that thing That that doesn't mean that
you can not start using You can start
using also LLMs and maybe local image
models to improve the speed and accuracy
of that testing.
Because it's also possible that right
now with some
uh very
small models that can actually do web
testing pretty good, even locally
without consuming cloud tokens.
Super interesting. So, let's actually
shift into this sort of local models uh
path, and just to sort of wrap up a bit
this sort of uh web MCP. It sounds like
um you know, you should like I guess
kind of everybody trying to kind of keep
up on this sort of content. So, if
you're if you have an elaborate uh web
applications on it, you should stay on
top of it. It's in experimental mode,
which again, I assume it will graduate
out of uh
appropriate to the sort of the pace of
change
uh that is in the AI as probably a
reasonable bet. Uh and it is uh
currently focused on interactive
websites and visible browsers. And I
guess kind of the people that need to be
most attuned to it are probably people
that are either looking to block bots
and things like that like that post on
X, or uh people that want to enable
browser-side functionality like
purchasing in e-commerce. Yeah, sounds
like a good summary. If you want to try
now, you need Chrome uh 146
and enable the flag,
and you need to install an extension
that is called model context tool
inspector that will let you debug your
web MCP code. And it's pretty simple, so
you don't need to spend like 2 months of
training or It's actually pretty simple
to implement. Hey everyone. Hope you're
enjoying the episode so [music] far. Our
team is working really hard behind the
scenes to bring you the best guests so
we can have the most informative
conversations about agentic development.
Whether that's talking about the latest
tools, the most efficient workflows, or
defining best practices. But for
whatever reason, many of you have yet to
subscribe to the channel. If you're
enjoying the podcast and want us to
continue to bring you the very best
content, please do us a favor and hit
that subscribe button. It really does
make a difference and lets us continue
to improve the quality of our guests and
build an even better product for you.
All right, back to the episode. Yeah,
probably the harder question is is to
sort of think about this mindset and
say, what are the actions that you want
and what are the user flows as opposed
to the technical complexity of it. Yeah.
I'm correct. And so, let's let's move a
bit to that sort of model. So, the other
topic that I've sort of seen you
you know, kind of discuss and and you
know, been been kind of tracking at the
cutting edge of uh is this whole world
world of of models within the browser,
you know, actually
you know, like we talk about uh you
know, giving an interface now to a to an
external browser that is agentic, but
this is literally within the web page, I
think, browsers. So, first of all, tell
us like I know there are two modes
there, right? Of sort of ship your own
model
uh versus something that's in the
browser. Like, what is this world of of
browser built
uh
models? As of today, most
uh if not all
um
AI-based API or apps powered by AI are
using the cloud. I mean, it seems like
the normal situation, you're consuming
tokens from Gemini, from um OpenAI, from
Claude, from whatever provider cloud
provider that is actually inferring your
models or the models you want in the
cloud, and you're paying for that. But
that's that's cloud AI. That's the
standard today. But there is another way
that is growing every year that right
now it's called web AI. I'm not sure if
all the developers actually
are using that name, or client-side AI.
Mhm.
>> And when you go to that with the web AI,
the idea is that you would execute
AI models, even LLMs, locally
on users' devices.
So, we are not talking about executing
locally on your web server. It We're
talking about the client, so Mhm. the
users' uh device. And for that, maybe
you're thinking, well, but we don't have
the power of ChatGPT. Yeah, of course,
we don't have the power of the latest
Opus 4.6, but the thing is that on a lot
of cases, you don't need that power.
Mostly when you are when you are
integrating AI in a web app, maybe you
just want to, for example, categorize a
post.
You want to check if the user is using
any hate in the text, or if it's uh
adding insults or whatever, you want to
filter that, and you don't need the
latest Opus 4.6
to do that. So, you can use a very small
model
that it works perfectly for that, and
it's going to be cheaper for you
because you don't need to pay for the
cloud. And you were talking about like
that uh uh
>> uh just sort of clarify, is this about
like a web model? So, it's different.
Like, a part of this don't pay for the
cloud, run locally is already available
as well by running actually sometimes
even like decent-sized models, not Opus,
uh on your machine through Ollama or
like one of these systems. Or LM Studio,
yeah. Yeah. But this one is something
that that's in between, or like well,
it's like maybe a uh
another another variant. To be honest,
it's the same. The difference is that
with Ollama or LM Studio, you're
downloading your models to your
computer. And in this case, the models
will be downloaded and executed in the
browser for the user without the user
even knowing that.
So, the user doesn't need to install
anything. The user doesn't need to
understand about models.
The The model is already on the user's
computer, and that's the first mode to
execute this.
Uh that's a built-in model
that right now
that will will be basically be available
on a lot of browsers. Today, only Chrome
is supporting that feature. That's
built-in AI.
So, in that case, if you have Chrome
right now on desktop, this is on desktop
right now. Android is coming. Right now,
it's on on desktop only.
Chrome can download uh
a small version of Gemini, Gemini Nano.
And it's available client-side to infer
from JavaScript from any website. Cool.
So, then if Gemini Nano is uh that is
even smaller than Gemini Flash
the one that is on the cloud.
But for a lot of For example, you can
translate content. Um it's pretty good
at translation. I think that the test is
like there are 25 languages where that
passes the test, so it's pretty good.
And you can translate content completely
client-side
just by using a JavaScript API that
talks to a local model that is already
in the user's Chrome. You said that
Chrome can install. Like, is it If I'm
writing a webpage, can I assume that
it's there? Because by default, when you
install Google Chrome, the model is not
there. The first website that requests
the usage of this API will actually say
will download
the model for the first time, will
install the models on users' devices,
and it will be available for the rest of
the website, for that website, another
website. How big is it? Like, what What
is the size of that?
>> 8 GB. Something like that. So, that's
why it's not coming with Chrome. Yeah,
yeah. It's not a small investment in
terms of a
>> But once it's downloaded, it's between 4
and and 8 because actually there are
three models, not one. So, based on what
are you requesting, it will download one
or the other. But it's between 4 and 8
GB, so yeah. It's It's It's more than
Chrome itself. So, that's why it's not
built-in with Chrome yet, but maybe in
the future it's going to be built-in
with the OS.
So, maybe we're heading towards that
future, right? So, then the browser will
just ask the OS, "Hey, do you have a
model?" And the OS will say, "Yes, we
have these models." And then the website
will just execute it locally. So, I I
think that we are heading towards that
future.
And
So, that's one way to execute models
locally, to use built-in APIs that today
is Chrome only, which is good, but
okay, not good enough to say I will use
this and nothing else.
And the other way
is to use libraries. [snorts]
And today, there there are there are
some low-level APIs on every browser,
including Safari, including Firefox. And
that's
WebAssembly
to use the CPU, WebGPU to use the GPU.
And now on some operating system, you
have WebNN
neural network that actually if you have
a a computer that has an special AI chip
inside, it can actually use it
from JavaScript. So, and on top of these
three APIs that are low-level, there are
a lot of open-source libraries.
Uh there are
like eight different libraries now from
Chrome, from different providers that
you can use that can run
models
using CPU, GPU, or
uh AI chips, the TPUs or there are
different names for that, MPUs. And so,
that means that your JavaScript, your
web app can download
an open-source model.
You can download Llama. You can download
uh Gemma from Google.
And you say, "Well, it it it it can be
Now you have some versions that are half
a GB, so 500 MB."
You can download that in JavaScript and
then execute it client-side on an
iPhone.
Uh it works in in Safari, in a website.
Yeah.
>> So, again, it depends on what do you
need to do.
Maybe it's it's not for for using uh for
for a therapist, okay? Or for for uh
teaching users history because those
models are not pretty good for that. But
but for summarizing, categorizing,
to actually for chat for support
chatbots, you can create your mini rug.
So, rug is a like a an architecture that
will let you connect your data with an
LLM. So, you can make a support chatbot
that talks to your own um information
with those LLMs.
And in that case, you the cost of the
inferring cost happens client-side.
Right.
>> So, it's it's being executed
client-side. And you always need to fall
back into a cloud API. So, and now
Google is offering a Firebase API that
will
execute client-side and as a fallback,
it will execute a model server-side.
>> uh yeah.
If it couldn't run
>> reason, yeah, the model can't be uh
inferred or executed uh client-side.
Yeah. I think that's uh it's super
interesting
uh as you as you think about sort of
future capabilities and use cases for
it. It sounds like right now, I mean,
the numbers sound a little bit scary
until you compare them to like a YouTube
video, right? Or stuff like that, right?
Like they It's not really that massive a
deal to download, you know, half a half
a GB, right? Or
uh or something like that. It's not
something you would want to every every
page loads to uh to require. No, but
remember that also you can use APIs to
store that offline. So, then
if it's a
recurring user, it's just a one-time
download, yeah. But but it's a an
interesting opportunity to provide
things that are
um you know,
I guess kind of reduce, you know, one
one optimization or like value
proposition that you mentioned is is one
of costs. And so, you might not need to
worry about everybody hammering your
support bot or your translation bot. The
two is probably some element of latency.
I guess that depends. Sometimes the
cloud servers will be faster.
Uh but there might be cases Well, it
depends on the case, actually. But for
some reason, for for image issues, for
example, the latency it's um it's equal,
so it's the same. For text, it depends
on how much text you're sending.
Uh if it's a very small, like you are uh
lay- having a label to something,
sometimes the local model yeah, it works
really fast. Yeah. And then I guess on
top of all that, there's also like the
privacy or the security aspect of it,
which is if you want to allow in certain
SaaS applications, you know, to allow
some functionality to happen only on the
client-side, right? There's a bunch of
these, you know, end-to-end encryption
functionality and things like that, so
the server actually never sees the data
at the moment that, you know, might get
translated to, and therefore you cannot
use LLMs on it. But if you're running
them locally, those might be reasonable,
right? Within WhatsApp, right? Like
within your app. Yeah, also also we need
to maybe stop thinking on LLMs as the
only solution. So, there are models that
are uh specifically targeting one use
case. So, for example, Apple released an
open-source model to detect um to to do
some kind of image detection. So, I
don't know, you can you can put
something on the camera, it will tell
you, "Oh, this that's ice breakers means
cinnamon." Yeah, I like those ones. And
and and that it's maybe 200 MB. It's a
model of 200 MB and works client-side.
So, now you can have an OCR system that
can detect objects um
completely local. So, it it opens uh lot
of opportunities for a lot of apps and
web apps that can run even without
internet, just offline,
and can be very specific for for some um
use cases. And And it actually works.
And you don't need LLMs. You need a
model that was specifically created for
that purpose. Yeah. It's interesting.
It's probably
You needed LLM in the ecosystem probably
to create those models cuz they probably
are distilled versions of a larger
>> Yeah, sometimes they are. and optimized.
Uh but the the L, you know, like I guess
in this case, it's neither L nor L,
right? It's neither large nor uh nor
language, you know, necessarily.
Uh it is kind of an image model, which I
guess is a language model of sorts. But
yeah, but based on what you said, right
now you can download There is a a new
version, for example, of
uh Qwen, the the Chi- one of the Chinese
models, that the 0.5 billion parameters.
That one is really small, and you can
fine-tune it.
So, I say So, then you can have a very
small LLM that is pretty bad at uh with
facts, okay? But you can fine-tune that
model in your computer. You don't need a
very large computer to fine-tune that
with your information. And then you have
a pretty decent LLM small that knows
about your stuff and can be executed
locally on every device, even mobile
phones. I think that is important in in
terms of like the trajectory of of the
industry cuz I mean, I would say that
today, you're probably on the cutting
edge if you're doing that, and you need
to be quite thoughtful. Like, there's
probably, you know, of all the people,
you know, listening, you know, and kind
of engaging with uh with these
technologies, probably a very small
fraction have use cases that they need
right now that truly match the the kind
of cost as in efforts uh versus reward
uh on it. But I I do believe that open
models, and I I don't think I'm unusual
in that sense, that open models are
getting much, much better and they will
get better you know, at AI speed, right?
They tend to lag six-ish months, you
know, behind
behind the world. So,
tuning in, you know, might further close
the gap if you have enough of a specific
use case. But even without it, I think
as a as a competency to build, if you're
building a new business, if you're
building a new kind of
interaction approach, you know, for your
application,
these are probably core capabilities you
should keep in mind thinking about what
needs to go to the server and what goes
on the client. I guess not dissimilar to
the thought of like the the
kind of the responsive websites, but
then even more like the the the rich the
progressive web apps
that run on the on the client side where
a lot of server-side functionality has
has moved to the client.
Right?
Yeah, that's right. Super interesting.
Who are there examples of like, you
know, who who who have you sort of seen
out there that's like most interesting
in terms of using AI
right now? That's a
like maybe like a
>> Client-side AI? Yeah. So, I've I've seen
a lot on the on the customer support
bots thing
because
they found that they can I mean, their
their tokens bill can get pretty high.
Mostly mostly when
they're
they're hacking their prompts and
they're so at some point they're losing
control on the money they're spending.
And so, I've seen that they're
interested in seeing if they can replace
that with client-side. So, if you want
to
uh
hack your prompt, go ahead, it's your
computer. So, it will be
you're hacking your own your own model.
So, I don't care if you do that. So, I
think it's it's about cost at some
point, right? Because um
everything is fine when you're doing
I mean, your first project, you release
a project, your MVP. I mean, yeah, maybe
it's a 50 bucks, you're okay. But when
you're scaling that Yeah. Maybe you
receive a bill of $100,000 of tokens
that you need to pay. And when you look
at that bill, you say, "Well, let's see
if we can cut this with
without without
like um
changing the quality of of the service
by moving some parts
to the client. Yeah, it's so
interesting. It's like it's funny cuz it
feels like
it's like an escalation
level, right? You're talking to the
front-line support, which is your local
model, and then, you know, it's like,
"No, no, no,
let me talk to your boss." And then you
go to the cloud, yeah, exactly. And then
you go to the to the cloud side, you
know, to to get it. It's also
interesting how support has become a bit
of a role model in terms of identifying
trajectory of application use for
for LLMs cuz probably, you know,
you can debate sort of software
development, but you know, you see the
pattern over there as well. But in
support, you definitely sort of saw
that, you know, be the first role to uh
I guess you can sort of say be
displaced. And in software development,
I I have this sort of intro slide for
Tesla on it and they talk about agentic
development kind of traits. And one of
the ones I have on there is that it's
cheap then expensive. Um because like
it's initially cheap because a single
person can do so much, you know, so it's
so much cheaper. And then you get the
bill, it's like,
"Do I need to be spending that much? Can
I can I do this
a bit more cost-effective?" But most
people are not there yet. Like most
people are
are still in the discovery phase. And
so, it's interesting to think about
support being kind of the forerunner
over there. Now, this is this is getting
better and better every year. So, it's
still I mean, if you if if we look at
some data that we don't have, I think
that probably
companies using client-side AI
are less than 1%. So, but
it's getting better and better in terms
of quality and cost and performance.
So, if other browsers, I don't know,
maybe Safari with now the new open
intelligence
contract with Google, maybe they will
also do something similar in Safari, so
they might get a local model local side
and
on the the local side. So, if that
happens, well, maybe we will see more
built-in AI
APIs
in in web apps. Yeah, I think I think
that makes perfect sense and it's always
hard to imagine how that doesn't work. I
guess one thing we didn't talk about in
the context of web AI is the sandboxing
of the
of the browser. And I guess if you
if you operate in this fashion compared
to an Ollama or whatever it is, you're
still working within the sandbox. So, if
you have two tabs,
Mhm. I guess minus the sort of sharing
capabilities that, you know, browsers
support,
in theory, each of them will have its
own copy, its own sort of data set. So,
one malicious website wouldn't be able
to sort of siphon off, you know, there's
probably going to be some set of
vulnerabilities, but today, you know,
putting those aside, wouldn't be able to
siphon off another tab's information.
Yeah, correct. That's correct. Yeah,
also we need to remember that the LLM is
a still a today a black box that you
send input and it gets you something
back.
So, if
in this case, two websites will send
different inputs and
they're not tied together in any way.
It's just two two prompts to the same
LLM. So, the security thing is going to
be the same with or without the LLM.
That's what I'm saying. Yeah, yeah, but
but it's interesting to think about I
think
so so all this conversation, you know,
really revolves around the sort of the
browser as the AI sandbox, right? And
and how
you know, you can
have the browser since the browser is
the entry point to the world and to your
systems and to your data in so many
fronts on it. How do you get it to
interact with agents? And increasingly,
we have, you know, the rise of the
agentic browsers and so very much the AI
sandbox and that's in the web MCP land
and, you know, create better interaction
points, many of which revolve around
security, authentication, purchase. It's
about trust delegation, right? Sort of
actions that you might
bump up. And so, I think that's very
interesting. And then you can augment
all of those with some local element LLM
action that is that is
part of your browser, which is
independent of the other path, but they
also point to the browser will have LLM
capabilities itself. So, maybe in the
first layer, it's more about like a
brokering or an interface layer, but
increasingly, it might actually embody
the engine to to perform activities. So,
from a from a website builder
perspective, first you need to think
about how do agents interact, and then
you need to think about how do you embed
agentic functionality literally into
your local web, right? Yeah. Also, I
think this will become more important
because even when some people thinks
again for the probably nth time that the
web is dying. So, if you think about
that, by coding and all these new apps
that are appearing because AI is coding
them, our web apps.
So, actually, the web is growing, not
dying.
So,
and I think that that means that we will
have more opportunities than even before
then to actually start thinking and
using these new architectures. Yeah,
super interesting. So, I guess, you
know, maybe to to close off,
if you can kind of take out your crystal
ball and, you know, we've sort of seen
the journey on how responsive web
applications, I'm not even sure if I'm
using sort of the word. That was that
was the name that I uh you know, moved a
little bit away from the web in my
The rich internet application, that's
Rich internet application. RIAs
are RIAs now, not the RIA. The rich
internet applications have become, you
know, the I don't know if they're the
norm everywhere, but like in in many in
many facets of applications, they have
become the way to build many apps and a
lot of functionality moved to the
client. I guess what what what is your
if you if you dare to cast your eyes 3
years out even, right? In the world of
of AI,
do do you envision there's going to be
applications that really innovate and
that this will become the norm to have
substantial in-browser, in-website
LLM functionality? So, I think that
yeah, so in in the future, we will see
less native apps
and more at least on on mobile devices
because maybe on the desktop, there is a
nowadays a new approach that a lot of
people are doing native apps, which is a
security problem, but anyway,
on the mobile world, I think more more
more web apps actually in the future.
Without maybe without using the term,
it's just a link, it's just a QR code,
it's just
an interface that users are using or
agents are using.
And maybe we are not going to call them
web apps anymore, just AI apps or apps
by coded apps or however you want to
call that. It's going to be web. And on
that, I think that
the the price and the quality of local
AI will improve a lot in the next few
years,
which will trigger a lot of new use
cases of local AI. Not all of them will
be local, not all of them will be web
apps, but a lot I'm seeing a lot of them
moving into that future that will be
faster and probably more performant.
Yeah, super interesting. And it's funny
how every every time the web gets
stronger, it raises this debate of why
do you even need native? You know, can I
can I just have it be the web? And I
guess there's a claim here that if
functionality becomes more agentic, if
more if the interfaces actually get
simpler because they get very
um kind of chats driven, right? Or sort
of, you know, natural
Like API based. You're you're you're
you're you're picking up that gauntlet
again, right? You're sort of picking the
glove, whatever it is, and saying, you
know, you think this debate will come up
again and and the web will win. Yeah, I
think so.
Cool. Max, thanks a lot for coming in in
those super interesting conversation. I
think exciting new frontier, you know,
for for the web. It sounds like it's
still
like today today probably still for the
pioneers and maybe for the e-commerce
shops
or or those who really care about
controlling agentic behaviors.
But
again, this is kind of AI pace. So, it's
probably going to become relevant to
many many more very quickly. So, thanks
for sharing the great information coming
here on the podcast.
My pleasure. Thank you.
And thanks everyone for tuning in and I
hope you join us for the next one.